无法了解若那丛林的无限始于我身
"CAN NOT KNOW IF THE JUNGLE INFINITE BEGAN IN ME
那过程带着我剩余的躯壳前往疯狂与无法弥补
THE PROCESS THAT TOOK THE OTHER TO MADNESS TOTAL and irremediable.
若有机会的话，只有我歉意的遗体与你的了解
IF AT ALL, ONLY ME RESTA APOLOGISE AND YOUR UNDERSTANDING,
如同我见证那未知的时光是如此迷人
AS THE UNFOLDING I witnessed THESE HOURS WAS SUCH Charmed
而我似乎不可能用字汇描述
ME THAT SEEMS IMPOSSIBLE TO DESCRIBE IN WORDS
让其他人能够理解它们的美丽与璀璨
THAT ALLOW THE OTHER understand their BEAUTY AND SPLENDOR.
我只知道，当我归来时，托纳多是我同时也是其他人
ONLY I KNOW, when I returned, TORNADO WAS ME ANOTHER MAN. "
席奥多·马蒂乌斯 亚马逊 1909年
THEODORE OF MARTIUS, AMAZON, 1909th
本字幕由Peace_Wang基于英文字幕翻译
- Art Subs - 7 years making art for you!
仅供学习与帮助理解剧情之用
Pirandelo legend
欢迎来信指教Email:v12123310@gmail.com
Synchrony and Review lletaif | Durenkian
犹库纳
Yukuna.
图卡诺
Tukano.
婚姻
Marriage.
- 科布瓦? - 滚开
- Kobeua? - Go away.
滚开!
Go away!
你是翻转天地的库拉美卡德吗?
You Karamate, which moves worlds?
你想干嘛?
What you want?
我是曼杜卡，努布库里之子，长屋寇美隆
I Manduca, son of Ruibukuri, the longhouse Komeilemong.
- 我是河畔巴拉人 - 我知道巴拉人
- I am the river bara. - I know the Baras.
你们没作战就直接投降白人
You surrendered to white without a fight.
你想干嘛
What you want?
这是埃斯特·席奥多·冯·马蒂乌斯
Este e Theodor von Martius,
是我的朋友与旅伴
My friend and travel companion.
他病得很重
He is very sick.
所有附近的巫师都没办法治好他
All the neighbors shamans tried to cure him. No one could.
巫师们说你们是唯一能帮助我们的人
They said you were the only one who can help us.
我才不像你们
I'm not like you.
我们不会救白人的
Not help the whites.
他是个聪明人，来这边学习的
He is a wise man, who came to learn.
你不救他，他会死的!
He will die if they do not help you!
你从哪里得到这个的?
Where did you get this?
放开!
Drop it!
你从哪里得到这个的?
Where did you get this?
什么?
What?
这个项链!
The collar!
这是一个科瓦诺巫师给我的礼物
It was a gift from a cohiuano shaman.
骗子!
Liar!
科瓦诺人早就不存在了!
The cohiuanos not exist!
他们还在
There are, yes.
我好几年前曾和他们相处
I've been with them a few years ago.
骗人!
Lie!
这是礼物
Ayumpari.
我没骗人，仍有些科瓦诺人住在亚里河
I'm not lying. Some of them were by the river Yari.
人数不多，但还存在
They are few, but still exist.
科瓦诺人早就不在了
The cohiuanos no longer exist.
你们杀了所有人
You killed everyone.
我不会帮你们的
I will not help you.
没事，曼杜卡
It's okay, Manduca. It's all right.
没事
It's all right.
只有亚库纳可以救你
Only yakruna can save you.
如果科瓦诺人还在的话，他们会有
If cohiuanos still exist, they will have.
否则你就会死
Otherwise, you will die.
亚库纳可以治好我?
The yakruna can cure me?
我的族人还活着吗?
My people still exist?
这个丛林很脆弱，如果你伤害它，它会复仇
The jungle is fragile, and if you attack, she retaliates.
只有尊敬它，它才会放我们走
She just let us go if we respect.
我们不该吃肉或鱼
we should not eat meat or fish
一直到雨再次落下
until the rain again
并征求动物之主的同意
and ask permission from the owners of the animals.
我们不能砍断任何树苗
We can not cut any tree in the bud.
月亮出来以前，不能和女人做爱
If we find a woman, do not have sex until the moon change.
接受吗?
Accepted?
席奥，你已经不能旅行了
Theo, you're in no condition to travel.
我不能死在这里
I can not die here.
接受吗?
Accepted?
你最好说实话
You better be telling the truth.
这个治疗只能减轻病情
This remedy only distracts the disease.
祂回来之后会变得更严重
When she comes back, comes back stronger.
是真的，我曾和他们相处过
It is true. I've been with them.
梦游亚马逊/蛇之拥抱
图卡诺
Tukano.
安都可
Andoke.
卡里荷娜
Karihona.
穆因
Muin.
你看得到我?
Can see me?
席奥多·冯·马蒂乌斯这个男人在40年前
40 years ago, this man, Theodor von Martius,
在这里写下我所追求的植物
He was here and wrote about the plant I seek.
我想知道他写的是否属实
I want to know if what he wrote is true.
我把生命奉献给了植物
I dedicate my life to plants.
把你的生命奉献给植物?
Dedicate your life to plants?
这是我所听过白人的话中最有理的
It's the most sensible thing I ever heard a white say.
我叫做伊凡
My name is Evan.
我是库拉美卡德
My name was Karamakate.
我从瓦纳诺人的长屋那边的河流来的
I went down the river from the longhouse of Wanano people.
我在寻找一种植物叫做亚库纳
I'm looking for a plant. The yakruna.
这是什么样的植物
What plant is this?
我对他所知不多，我不知道是否在这
I know very little about it. I do not know if there is.
我想了解它
I want to learn about it.
马蒂乌斯描述它是一种可以治病的神圣植物
Von Martius described it as a sacred plant to cure diseases,
生长在橡胶树上并增加它的纯度
growing on the rubber and increases its level of purity.
这是你想要它的原因吗?
That's why you want it?
这是曼比吗?
This is Mambe?
你喜欢古柯叶?
You like our coke?
也想要亚库纳?
You want to yakruna too?
如果你帮忙，我可以给你很多钱
I can give you a lot of money if you help me.
非常多的钱
It's a lot of money.
钱就像蚂蚁
Ants like money.
我才不要，它的味道不好
I Do not. The taste is bad.
我从未做梦过
I never dreamed.
也不曾睡着或醒着
Neither asleep nor awake.
连死藤都对我没用
Not even the caapi took effect on me.
巴拉人、图卡诺人、西里安人的巫师
Shamans in the villages of Baras, the Tukanos and Sirian
告诉我只有亚库纳
I was told that only yakruna
可以拯救我
Would you help me.
我曾经梦到一个白人灵魂
I once dreamed of a white spirit.
他病了
He was sick
只有学会作梦才能治好他
and only learned to dream could be saved,
但他没有办到
but he could not.
你的梦对你来说很值钱吗?
Your dreams are worth a lot of money for you?
你知道哪里有亚库纳吗?
You know where to find yakruna?
你还有曼比吗?
You have more Mambe?
我还有一点古柯叶
I have a little coke.
怎么了?
Something wrong?
曼比忘了存在
Mambe forgot existed.
现在我不知道该怎么办
Now I do not know how to do.
你对亚库纳了解多少? 你有吗?
What do you know about yakruna? Where you have?
你不是一个人
You are not one.
你是两个人
You're two men.
我想看看亚库纳，我会跟你一起去
I want to see yakruna. I will go with you.
你知道路?
You know the way?
我不记得了
I do not remember.
你会带我走
You'll take me.
这全都是你做的?
You did all this?
你指什么?
What do you mean?
不知道，我不记得了
Do not know. I do not remember.
石头跟我说话，他们回答我的问题
These stones were talking to me. They answered my questions.
线破碎了，记忆也消失了
The line broke, the memories are gone.
石头，树木，动物，都沉默了
Stones, trees, animals, all were silent.
现在只有图画仍在这里
Now there is only the drawings on the rocks.
现在我空空如也，我是丛林的魂魄
Now I am empty. I Chullachaqui.
这像是亚库纳的生命画像
This seems a yakruna life drawing.
这是山脉
These are mountains.
一群山脉
A group of mountains.
这是众神的工坊
It is the "workshop of the Gods".
它就在这，亚库纳的所在
It is there, where there is a yakruna.
我怎么会忘了
How I forgot gifts
来自神的礼物?
from Gods?
我忘了如何做曼比
I forgot how to do Mambe.
我变成了什么?
What became?
太重了
We have too much weight.
我们必须丢下这些箱子
We need to get rid of the boxes.
不行，那些是我的箱子，我需要它们
No, they are mine. I need them.
箱子会让船沉掉，快丢掉它们
They will sink us. Throw them out.
这些箱子很有用处
They are useful.
想要的话可以看看
You can look if you want.
这不是他，这是魂魄
It's not him. It's Chullachaqui it.
什么?
What?
他看起来像是魂魄
The Chullachaqui it. It looks like it.
这是照片
It's a photo.
我们曾变成魂魄
It happened to us. We turned chullachaquis.
你见过他?
You met him?
你知道怎么回事吗?
You know how it is?
他年纪跟我相似吗?
He's old like me?
不
No,
他死在这个丛林
he died in this jungle.
他不曾离开过
He never turned away.
这是他给你的?
As he gave you this?
曼杜卡，他的伙伴
Manduca, his traveling companion,
他把马蒂乌斯的日记寄到德国
He sent daily him to Germany.
之后发行了这本书
They were published there.
曼杜卡，我们有什么可以交换杂货吗?
Manduca, we have something to exchange for groceries?
小东西
Little thing.
太神奇了
Amazing.
过来
Come.
你还好吧?
Are you alright?
感觉好一点没有?
It is better?
看看谁翻转了天地?
Found who moves the world?
这是库拉美卡德，他同意帮忙
This is Karamakate. He agreed to help.
我必须遵守禁令
I have to keep the prohibitions.
你需要力气才能旅行，吃吧
You need strength to travel. You can eat.
我可以吃吗?
I can?
过了库度亚立后，我要如何才能到亚里?
After Cuduyari, how do I get to Yari?
跟着乌拉里奎拉星就可以到以加拉河
Follow Uraricoera star to Rio Igara.
那是什么星?
What star is that?
是可以在日落位置看到的星
That which is visible at sunset there.
在那里?
For there?
这是什么?
What is it?
罗盘
A compass.
它永远指着同个方向
She always points
指着卡鲁纳星
para a Estrela de Auakaruna.
它的指针被地球的磁场吸引
The needle is attracted by the magnetic field of the Earth.
因为?
Because?
它永远能指着地球的能量方向
She always point where the Earth's energy indicates.
- 席奥，唱你的歌! - 不，别再来了
- Theo, sing your song! - No! Not again!
曼杜卡，我不会独唱
Manduca, I will not sing alone.
跟我一起唱!
Sing with me!
来吧
Come.
你是谁?
Who are you?
你怎么能一个人活在这样的丛林?
How can you live alone in a jungle like this?
曼杜卡
Manduca,
罗盘呢?
you are the compass?
没留在长屋?
Not left the longhouse?
谁偷走了我的罗盘?
Some of you took my compass?
还来
Give back.
快还来，小偷!
Give back, his thieves!
谁拿走了，快还来
Which of you is? Give back.
别碰他，席奥
Leave him, Theo.
我不能把罗盘留在这，曼杜卡
I can not leave a compass here, Manduca.
图恰瓦，告诉他们快还来
Tuschaua, tell them to give back.
拜托，图恰瓦，我需要它
Please Tuschaua, I need her.
我不要交换东西
I will not change it.
请还给我
Please return it.
拜托，图恰瓦，我需要它
Please Tuschaua, I need her.
拜托
Come on.
我说了，我需要我的罗盘
I said, I have my compass here.
怎么了?
What is?
你跟其他白人一样
You're like the other white.
他们的引路方法是由风向与星星判断的
The guidance system of them is based on the wind and stars.
如果让他们学会使用罗盘，这些知识都会失传
If you learn to use a compass, this knowledge will be lost.
你不能禁止他们学习
You can not forbid them to learn.
知识就是一切
Knowledge is all.
但你不懂，因为你是白人
But you do not understand, because it is white.
还好吗?
All right?
扔了吧
Leave it.
它们只是物品而已
They are just things.
不要
Do not.
为什么白人这么爱他们的东西
Why white love both your stuff?
它们只是物品而已
There are just things.
但它们是我与家乡德国
They are my only link
与德国的城市与朋友
my people in Germany, my city,
与我的妻子、孩子的连结
my wife, my children. These boxes contain
这些箱子里头有这四年来
all the knowledge gathered
我所旅行的一切经历
in four years of travel.
我必须带着它们...
I have to take them, but ...
因为没人会相信我的，所以扔了就是抛弃一切了
no one will believe me. Let them is to leave everything.
你疯了
You are crazy.
我知道
I know.
那是橡胶商人在你身上标记的?
The rubber barons have marked you?
是的，但现在我是自由人
Yes, but now I'm a free man.
卡利普拉肯纳蟒蛇是从这里
It was here that the anaconda down the Milky Way
带着我们的祖先从银河下来的吗?
karipulakena bringing our ancestors?
该死的橡胶!
damn rubber!
他说什么?
What is he saying?
他在求你杀死他
He is asking you to kill him.
你有带枪?
You brought a gun?
- 曼杜卡，怎么了? - 曼杜卡，不行!
- Manduca, what is it? - Manduca, do not!
曼杜卡，你不能这样做
Manduca, can not do that.
如果我不这样做，他们会折磨死他的
If I do not, they will torture him to death.
别这样做，曼杜卡
Do not do it, Manduca.
别这样!
Do not do it!
- 曼杜卡，不 - 没人应该受如此折磨
- Manduca, no. - No one deserves this hell.
不要这样，曼杜卡
Seems Manduca appears.
曼杜卡，不!
Manduca, no!
库拉美卡德
Karamakat to.
来吧
Come on.
我不要
I will not.
为什么?
Because?
不能相信白人
You can not trust whites.
我也没有相信你
I also have not because trust you.
你到底在干嘛?
So what are we doing?
这就是你的知识吗?火枪?
This is your knowledge? Firearms?
你们的科学只会带来暴力
His science only leads to this: "Violence".
死亡
Death.
你错了
Is not true.
你们还抢走了什么?古柯?
What else is stealing? Coke?
金鸡纳? 橡胶?
Quina? Eraser?
所以你想要抢走亚库纳?
So you want to steal yakruna?
接下来还有什么会死掉?
What else will turn into death?
别这样跟他说话
Do not talk to him like that.
他为我们族人做的比你们还多
He did more for our people than you.
所以呢? 看看你这身白人衣服
Is that you? Look at your white man's clothes!
你怎么能这样改变自己的文化?
How could you let that change their culture?
你想像他一样? 别妄想了
You think like them. Do not think anything.
你站在哪一边? 你这个杂种
Which side are you on? It is a mestizo.
我从没见过任何人比曼杜卡更忠诚
I never met anyone more loyal than Manduca.
他保卫自己的人民从未失败过，那你呢?
He never failed to defend his people. Is that you?
你做过什么?
What did you do?
你不过是孤立自己，好远离这个世界
He isolated like crazy, away from the world.
我什么东西都没偷过
I'm not stealing anything.
看看这个
Look here!
这是我在这学到的
This is my knowledge.
我想了解你们的世界
You also try to understand the world around them.
我想说你们的故事
You also tell stories.
我必须把这带回去给我的妻子，给我的人民
I have to take them to my wife, to my people.
这不是死亡，这是生命
This is not death, it is life.
这是我的音乐
This is my music.
这是什么?
What is this?
这是我画的
A drawing I did.
你从哪里看到这个?
Where did you see that?
从梦中
A dream.
用过死藤后的梦?
A dream caapi?
不，我没喝过死藤水
No. Never let me drink caapi.
我从梦中看到的
I saw in a dream.
我才不是杂种
I'm not a mestizo.
如果这些橡胶商人是人类，我就是蛇
If these rubber barons are men, I'm a snake.
那边失火了吗?
This is a fire?
不，那边是秘鲁人
No. They are Peruvians.
来吧
Come.
我们必须和死藤之主说话
We have to talk to the caapi master.
只有他可以解释
Only he can explain.
什么意思?
What you mean?
我曾梦过你那幅画作
I dreamed of your design.
这不可能
Impossible.
对领导者来说没有什么不可能
Nothing is impossible for the conductor.
准备好要喝了吗?
It is ready to drink?
我可以吗?
I can?
不要恐惧，喝下它吧
Drink without fear.
里面已经没了
Already it clean inside.
你再喝一次吧
You can drink again.
孩子
Baby.
你需要放松
You need to relax.
瓦托马
Watoima.
我不想死
I do not want to die.
为什么死藤之主不跟我说话
Why caapi master does not talk to me?
我不知道，这从来没发生过
Do not know. It never happened before.
你之前看到什么?
What you saw?
*死藤之主带我看到盎司草
The master took me to see an ounce.
他告诉我瓦托马碰到地面就会变好
He told me that Watoima turned good when touched the ground.
好去接受任务
Good received a mission.
什么任务
What mission?
杀了你
Kill you.
这个好是指我的状态吗?
This good is my condition?
不，是指别的事情
No, it's something else.
如果死藤之主不跟我说话
If the master caapi not talk to me,
那亚库纳还能帮助我吗?
the yakruna can still help me?
你不懂如何聆听，我必须好好教你
You do not know how to listen. I'll have to teach you.
猎豹有说过我的事情吗?
The jaguar said something about me?
祂要求我保护你
She asked me to protect you.
终于在昨天晚上，我有机会了解
Last night, at last, I had the opportunity
那许多年前在德国看见的
to understand the vision I had in Germany,
躺在她身边的景象·
lying beside her, many years ago.
我终于了解为何我幻想着盎司草
Finally I could understand why I imagined an ounce.
但无论我如何努力尝试
But no matter how hard I tried,
我如何想要
how I wanted to,
我仍然对死藤水的作用免疫
still totally immune to the effect of caapi.
我觉得我失败了，我的爱人
I feel I failed, my love.
我会强迫自己接受
I will be forced to accept that my colleagues were right
我同事对我这趟旅行的批评
when criticized my trip.
我害怕我和你的距离
I fear that distanced me from you
最后变成生与死的对望
only to die thousands of kilometers from our house.
我希望这病只是因为那强烈的渴望
I can only hope that this disease is caused by the great longing
因为他不在我身旁所致
by not having him by my side.
并且我乞求你原谅我对你所表达的暗生情愫
And I beg you to forgive me for express dark feelings.
我也希望，我的爱人
But also I hope, my love ...
你将发现我对你的感情
... You find in my honesty
是如此坚贞忠诚
another proof of my affection ...
怎么了? 你听得懂我说什么?
What's it? You understand me?
不是，是你看起来快哭了
No, but it looks like you're about to cry.
他在写信给他的妻子
He is writing to his wife.
我想对她表达我的情意
I like to express my affection for her.
对一个女人? 是指哭之前还是之后的情意?
For a woman? Before or after crying?
你才不懂
You do not understand.
你回去之后，也会对我表达你的情意吗?
When you return, will express their affection for me too?
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
一定要好好保存
Must be saved.
可是这是我
But it's me.
不，这只是影像而已
No, and you. It's an image.
像魂魄那样?
As chullachaqui um?
像什么一样?
One what?
魂魄
Um chullachaqui.
所有人都有这个魂魄
All have a Chullachaqui,
它看起来像我们，但他是空洞的
it seems to us, but it's empty, hollow.
这是一个时光的保存
This is a time of remembrance now.
魂魄没有记忆
A Chullachaqui has no memory.
他在这世界上到处徘徊
He just wanders around the world,
空洞，像鬼魂一样，被遗弃在时光之中
empty, like a ghost, lost in a time without time.
你会把我的魂魄给你的族人看?
Will show my Chullachaqui his people?
如果你同意才行
Only if you let it.
项链是科瓦诺人身体的一部份，不可以给别人
The necklace is part of cohiuanos. It can not be given.
好吧
Okay.
把桨拿靠近船一点
Keep the paddle closer to the boat.
听好，河会告诉你什么时候该划
Listen. The river tells you when paddling.
像这样吗?
Like this?
为什么不回到你族人身边
Why did not return to his people?
哥伦比亚人毁了一切
Colombian ended up with everything.
你曾经回去看过吗?
Did you ever go back and see?
那时我是个小孩
I was a child.
你怎么活下来的?
How did you survive?
另一个橡胶种植园?
Another rubber plantation?
不再是了
No longer.
上面写着这里有个修道院
It says here it's a mission.
我们停下来去补给一下吧
Let's stop and get groceries.
不，我们快走吧
No. Let's go.
我知道这个地方
I know this place.
适合补给吗?
As we groceries?
不是特别好
Not very well.
我们要停在这里
We will stop then.
嗨，小兄弟
Hi, little brother.
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
我叫做曼合卡纳莲佩
Manhekanalienipe.
这才不是你的名字，我们不能说族语
This is not your name! We can not speak the language.
我叫做耶利米
My name is Jeremiah.
牧师在哪里?
Where are the priests?
快走！
Go! Go!
我们这里没有橡胶树
We do not have rubber!
我们不要橡胶
We do not want rubber.
你们想干嘛?
What do you want?
我的名字是席奥多·冯·马蒂乌斯
My name is Theodor von Martius.
德国图宾根大学
Am ethnographer University of Tubingen
与斯图加特博物馆的民族志学者
and the Museum of Stuttgart, Germany.
这是我的伙伴曼杜卡与库拉美卡德
These are Manduca and Karamakate, my traveling companions.
你们想要什么?
What they want?
我们是来考察的
We are on an expedition
我们需要补给才能继续旅行
and we need food to continue our trip.
水果、木薯，什么都可以
Fruits, cassava, whatever.
我不在乎，给我滚
I do not care! Go away.
我们可以谈谈，我会付钱
We can negotiate, I have money. I can pay.
给我滚!
Go away!
我们走吧
Let's go.
他说什么?
What he said?
恶魔的语言可不能在这里说
demon languages ​​are not allowed here.
"你们若以为我是真信主的，
"If you judge me faithful to the Lord,
请到我家里来住·"
come to my house and stay in it. "
冷静点，我们需要点食物才能继续往前走
Calm. We can not move forward without food.
你是个修行之人，对吧?
You are capuchin, right?
拜托帮帮我们
Please help us.
我们会遵守你的规定
We will respect your rules.
只说西班牙语，我们是讲求科学的人
Only talk Spanish. We are men of science.
像圣汤玛斯·阿奎那
As St. Thomas Aquinas.
"不可忘记用爱心接待客旅，
"Do not forget to show hospitality,
因为曾有接待客旅的接待了天使..."
therefore "received my angels ...
"不知不觉就...
"Received" my angels
接待了天使"
... Many unknowingly. "
我怀疑你们是否是天使
I doubt that you are angels,
但在神的屋檐下我不能拒绝以爱心接待客人
but the house of God is not mine to refuse them hospitality.
欢迎来到帕多瓦的圣安多尼修道院
Welcome to St. Anthony of Padua Mission in Vaupes.
在雨降下以前不能吃鱼
It is forbidden to eat fish before the rain comes.
你在这里多久了?
How long are you here?
我在秘鲁人大屠杀之后来的
I came after the massacre of Peruvians.
不超过十年
No longer will make 10 years.
一直以来都只有你一个人?
He was alone all this time?
不是的
Do not.
马西林弟兄还有其他弟兄
Brother Marcellin and other brothers of the order
在两年前接到命令
They were looking for new disciples
去寻找其他信徒之后就没回来了
two years ago and never returned.
有在河边见过他们吗?
Not seen them down the river?
你只抢男人吗?
You only robs men?
我们有神圣的任务
Our mission is sacred
要拯救橡胶战争中的孤儿
to rescue the orphans of war rubber,
拯救他们的灵魂
to save their souls
让他们远离食人族与无知
and keep them away from cannibalism and ignorance.
向勇敢的哥伦比亚橡胶致敬
IN TRIBUTE TO COURAGE OF COLOMBIAN RUBBER,
它们为这片大地的食人族带来文明
THAT BROUGHT TO EARTH CIVILIZATION OF WILD cannibals
并向他们展现神的道路与祂的教堂
AND SHOWED THE WAY OF GOD AND HIS HOLY CHURCH.
牧师 拉斐尔·雷耶斯 - 1907年8月 哥伦比亚
RAFAEL REYES - PRES. COLOMBIA AUGUST 1907
给我一个锅子
Give me a pot.
我知道这边的生活是怎样的
I know what life is like here.
那些白人是疯子
The whites are crazy.
过来
Come.
过来吧，不要害怕
Come on, do not be afraid.
看，这是番茉莉
Look. This is chiricaspi.
我们的祖先卡利普拉肯纳战胜了众神
Karipulakena our ancestors won the gods.
祖先从太阳神那拿到他的精液
We received the semen of the Sun when Yeba, his daughter,
祖先把精液抹下并种入土壤里
He scratched his cock and planted the semen in the dust.
在敖煮这植物之前我们必须做同样的事情
We have to do the same thing with the plant before boiling it.
来帮我
Help me.
这是抵御疾病最佳的方式
This is the best defense we have against the disease.
它会帮助你们活下来
It will help you to survive.
那些人杀死我的族人时，牧师也带走了我
The priests also took me when they killed my people.
我的族人没有投降
They did not surrender.
他们拿起武器战斗
They fought.
这也是你们应该做的
That's what you need to do.
不要相信那个疯子
Do not believe this madness
吃下他们神的身体
eating the bodies of their gods.
他给你们食物
They give you food,
但是一点都不尊敬禁忌
but do not respect the prohibitions.
有一天这些森林中的食物都会被毁掉
The day will end with all the food from the forest.
你们还小，所以森林原谅你们
You are still small, so the forest forgive them.
死藤之主会引导你们
The caapi master will guide you.
每样植物、树木、花草都充满着智慧
Every plant, every tree, every flower is full of wisdom.
别忘记他们是什么、他们从哪里来
Never forget who they are and where they came from.
不要让你们的音乐消失
Do not let your music go away.
别碰我!
Do not touch me!
你们把恶魔带来这里了!
You brought the devil to the community!
你们让这些无辜的人被玷污!
You have perverted the innocent!
我们得走了
We have to go.
我们必须带走他们
We have to take them.
不行
We can not.
他们会杀死这些孩子的
They will kill them.
我们没办法喂饱他们
We can not feed them.
快跑
Run.
在哪里?
Where?
我不知道，你才是向导
Do not know. You are the guide.
你可以帮忙我
You could help me.
你在这什么都找不到的
You will not find anything there.
对橡胶有兴趣?
Interested in rubber?
我以前从没见过
I've never seen such.
橡胶代表死亡，你在寻找什么?
Rubber means death. So you are looking for?
你不是一个人
You're two men.
你是什么意思?
What you mean?
为什么你坚持跟着我却又不帮助我
Why do you insist on coming with me if you will not help me?
我想起来了
I remembered.
你想到什么了?
He recalled what?
想到那里可以找到亚库纳?
Where can we find yakruna?
我记得一件事，但不知道是什么意思
I remembered one thing, but do not know what it means.
也许我不是魂魄
Maybe I'm not Chullachaqui.
我们要去哪?
Where are we going?
往右边走
On the right.
我们会找到你在寻找的东西
We will find what you are looking for.
我们必须回去!
We have to go back!
我们不能回去
We can not go back.
他们已经在这里了
They are already here.
我以前没来过这里
I've been here before.
弥赛亚不接受访客
The Messiah will not receive visitors.
我们不是要见他
We do not want to see him.
我们只是跟着路走
we just follow our path.
这不可能
It's not possible.
这是我们的乐土你必须要守密
Eden of our community depends on your secret.
我们不会说出去的
We will not tell anyone.
让我看看你们有些什么
Show me what you have there.
这是礼物吗?
It's a gift?
你们是东方三贤者吗?
You are the Three Wise Men?
但只有看到你们两位，巴尔萨泽与梅尔基奥
But only see two of you, Balthazar and Melchior.
加斯帕在哪里?
Where is Caspar?
他迷路了
He has lost his way.
他因为背叛而被请去自杀了
He was invited to suicide, because his betrayal
他造成我们这边受尽疾病的折磨
It caused the disease that afflicts our community.
今天我们不会施展奇蹟
Today I do not do miracles!
所以你是麦姬?
So, you are the Magi?
我们是科学家
we are scientists
在寻找神圣的植物
looking sacred plants.
神圣的植物?
sacred plants?
这神圣的东西要杀死我!
The only sacred thing in this kills me!
库尔-纳
Cure-na.
她必须要送去医院治疗
They need to take her to a hospital.
这是利什曼原虫症，他们没办法治好她的
She's leishmaniasis. They will not be able to cure it.
弥赛亚今天心情不好
The Messiah is in a bad mood today.
但是她的妻子病了，我必须想办法
But his wife is ill. I also would look like.
我希望这有用
I hope it works.
我不想要你也被邀请去自杀
I would not want you to be invited to suicide.
这太疯狂了
This is crazy.
你不在乎吗?
Does not care?
没错，有些事情不对劲
Yes. Something went wrong.
现在他们是...
Now they are ...
在两个世界中最糟的部分
in the worst of both worlds.
感谢主
Thank the Lord.
拿走所有饮料
Tomai todos e bebei.
这杯是我的血液
This is the cup of my blood,
这是崭新与永恒的盟约
the new and eternal covenant.
闭嘴!
Cala mouth!
哦，神圣的麦姬
Oh, Holy Magi,
从东方远道而来
that viestes do Oriente
我知道要循你的道路去伯利恒
I know find on your way to Bethlehem.
对饮料给予祝福!
Gives blessing to our drink!
他治好了我的妻子
He healed my wife,
现在他会治好我们
and now he will heal us!
兄弟姊妹们庆祝这喜乐的一天!
Irmaos celebrate this day of joy!
Jack-o!
我不能和上帝之子同饮一杯酒
I can not drink from the same glass as the son of God.
上帝之子
The son of God.
上帝之子! 我是弥赛亚
The son of God! I am the Messiah,
印地安人的救世主
the Redeemer of Indians!
上帝之子，上帝的羔羊!
The son of God, Agnus Dei!
吃了我! 吃了我!
Me coma! Me coma!
吃了我!
Me coma!
各位，快吃了我!
Everyone, eat me! Eat!
吃下去，这是上帝的身躯
Eat, it is the body of God!
船太重了
It has too much weight.
你在干嘛?
What are you doing?
别烦我!
Stop bothering me!
这些箱子跟你有仇吗?
What is your problem with these boxes?
你在乎的事情只会引领你走向疯狂与死亡
Your things will only lead you to madness and death.
你是什么意思? 你对他们下毒!
What you mean? You poisoned them!
我没有下毒
I will not poisoned.
我只不过给了他们能好好思考的东西
Just I gave them something to think better.
他们是马固人，不是蟒蛇的后代
They are Makus. Not born of anaconda.
他们比人类还不如
They are less than humans.
你就像个橡胶商人
You look like a rubber baron.
跟他们一样，你一直在骗我
It is equal to them. You're lying to me.
你还记得所有事情吗
Do you remember everything.
别走
Do not go.
我觉得自己仍像个魂魄
I still feel like a Chullachaqui.
但我开始想起来了
But I'm starting to remember.
我的任务是通知我的族人
My mission was to inform my people,
但那些橡胶商人与哥伦比亚人来了
but the rubber barons and Colombians came.
而我独自一人
And I was alone.
我一定要想起来
I must remember.
我必须保留着科瓦诺人的音乐
I need to keep the music of cohiuanos.
你会告诉我方向吗?
You will show me the way?
我不知道，你必须自己去找
I do not know him. You have to find out.
把你的行李丢掉
Play your luggage out.
好了，满意了吗?
Ready. Satisfied?
给我看看那箱子
Show me that box.
我不会让你丢掉它的
I will not let you throw it away.
这是禁忌
Me exhibitions.
这是什么?
What is it?
这音乐抚慰了我
This music soothes me.
带我回到我爸爸在波士顿的房子，回到我的祖先那
Take me to my father's house in Boston, to my ancestors.
要变成战士
To become warriors,
科瓦诺人必须放下一切
the cohiuanos must abandon all
被梦境引导，独自一人前往丛林
and go alone to the jungle, guided only by their dreams.
在旅程中，他必须找到
In this journey, he has to find out,
在那孤独与沉寂之中，真正的他是谁
in solitude and silence, who he really is.
他必须变成一个漫步者的梦
He must become a wanderer dream.
许多人迷失了，有些人则永远没回来
Many are lost, and some never return.
但是那些回来的人
But those who return
他们已经准备好面对即将来临的一切
They are ready to face what is to come.
在何方?
Where are?
母亲对着孩子的歌唱在何方?
Where are the songs that sang mothers to babies?
长老们的故事在何方?
Where are the stories of elders,
那爱情的耳语，漫长的战斗呢?
the whispers of love, battle chronic?
你要往何方?
Where do you go?
你做梦了吗?
You dreamed?
告诉我你梦到什么
Tell me what you dreamed.
我什么也没梦到
I did not dream anything.
你说谎，我看见一双作着梦的眼睛
You're lying. He saw the eyes of Oz.
我说没有!
I'm saying no!
你在害怕
Is afraid,
但是你必须聆听
but you have to listen.
梦才不会吓到我
Dreaming does not scare me.
死亡才是我唯一惧怕的
Die in this hell I'm afraid.
你正让我抓狂
You're driving me crazy
用你那些梦境与狗屁禁忌
with your dreams and shit bans.
快停下来，你没有允许不能抓鱼!
Stop it. You can not fish without permission!
谁的允许?
Permission from whom?
你的吗?
Your?
还是鱼的主人?
Fish owner?
遵守你的狗屁禁令让我作呕
Respect your shit bans keeps me sick!
冷静，席奥，你正在妄想
Calm, Theo, you're delusional!
放开我!
Let me go!
你也想杀死我吗?
You want to kill me too?
放开那长矛!
Let go of the spear.
这条河里都是满满的鱼
The river is full of fish!
我不会停下来的!
I will not finish them!
你要怎么帮忙?
How can you help?
忘记他们对你所做的事情?
Forgotten what they did to you?
这不是他的错，他还清了我在种植园的债务
It was not him. He repaid my debt in the plantation.
然后你就变成他的奴隶
And you become his slave.
我才不是奴隶
I'm no slave no.
我需要他，他可以教导我白人的事情
I need him. He can teach white.
如果他一点都不尊敬丛林该如何学习?
How can he learn it does not respect the jungle?
他吓坏了，但是仍可以学习
He's scared, but you can learn.
他是他族人的英雄，所有人都敬仰他、聆听他
He is a hero to his people. All they admire and listen.
如果白人不好好学习，这会变成我们的末日
If whites do not learn, will be our end.
所有一切都会毁灭
The end of everything.
你没事吧?
Kariauatinga, are you okay?
白人可真厉害
The whites are awesome!
他们什么都吃然后就完蛋了
They eat everything they see to explode!
你必须学会控制自己
You have to learn to control.
别什么都吃
It's eating everything!
他还好吗?
How is he?
不能再好了
Best.
快给他太阳的精液
Give semen from the Sun to him.
你必须救他，让他不再心痛
You have to help him. No more heartache.
他的身体已经再次污浊了，给他只会害死他
His body is dirty again. It would be like giving poison to him.
我们必须快回到我的族人身边
We have to come soon to my people
然后跟亚库纳说话，请求原谅
and talk to yakruna ask to forgive.
我们很接近了
We are very close.
吃了这个，明天你会感觉好一点的
Tomorrow you will feel better. With the.
在这里
Is here.
在左边
To the left.
停下来!
Stopped!
哥伦比亚人?
Colombian?
别动!
Do not move!
你是哥伦比亚人?
You are Colombians?
我不知道
Do not know.
快滚出这里!
Get out of here!
瑟古来了
Sirgu arrived.
喝点亚库纳
Drink some yakruna.
敬世界末日!
It's a toast to the end of the world!
你怎能允许这种事?
How can you allow this?
怎么可以?
How can?
亚库纳是不该被栽种的
The yakruna should not be cultivated.
是我误解了这些迹象，它们如此清楚
I misunderstood the signs. They were clear.
你太好了
You are good!
你就是那条蛇
You are the snake!
冷静
Calm.
还给我
Give me back.
你不配拥有这个
You do not deserve this!
你们把死亡与地狱带来这片大地!
You bring hell and death to the earth!
哥伦比亚人来了!
Colombians are coming!
亚库纳就在这里!
Here is yakruna!
但知识比我的族人更重要!
The more knowledge than my people!
我不会让你得到它的
I will not let you take it.
永不!
Never!
哥伦比亚人来了!
Colombians are coming!
库拉美卡德!
Karamakat to!
接下来的故事呢?
What story is counting?
神是如何创造天地的
How God created the world.
就像这首歌一样，听好
The way is this song. Listen.
多么美丽
Is beautiful,
但不过就是个故事
but it's just a story.
这不是故事
It's not a story.
这是一场梦，你应该跟随着他
It is a dream. You should follow him.
我是个科学家，只认识事实
I am a scientist, real facts, palpable.
我不能被我的梦境引导
I can not be guided by dreams that I have.
但你仍跟随着
But you follow.
这条河上有几个河岸?
How many banks are there in this river?
两个
Two.
说给我听听
As you know?
有一个与另一个
It has one and other.
一加上一等于二
One plus one equals two.
你怎么知道的
How do you know that?
因为就像这样，一加一等于二!
Because it's like this! One plus one equals two.
你错了
You are wrong.
这条河有着3个、5个，上千个河岸
This river has three, five, thousand margins.
小孩子都明白，不像你这样，这条河是蟒蛇之子
Children understand. Not you. The river is the son of anaconda.
我们从梦境中学习，但它们都是真的
We learned in our dreams, but it's true,
比你所说的事实还要更真
more real than what you call "real".
你看到什么了?
What do you see?
这个世界如此巨大
The world is so huge.
但你却选择看这张纸
But you choose to see it.
这世界会说话，我知道聆听
The world speaks. I just know listen.
聆听着祖先的音乐
Listen to the music of their ancestors.
这就是你寻求的道
It is the way you seek.
聆听真理，不只能用你的耳朵
truth hear. Not only with your ears.
给我一点好吗
Give me a little?
你不聆听的话我不会给你任何东西的
I will not give you anything to decide to hear.
给我一点死藤水好吗?
Give me a bit of caapi?
如果你不相信你自己，死藤水不会帮助你的
Caapi will not help if you do not want to believe you.
你能帮助我吗?
Can you help me.
我只能做到这样了
I can only do this.
这是哪里?
Where?
你了解多少?
How do you know?
我就是知道
I know.
好好想想
Think.
这就是众神的工坊吗?
It is the workshop of the Gods?
一定要来到这里
It was necessary to come here.
快看!
Look!
准备好了
Is ready.
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
这还没受伤，我们要好好保存它
Not damaged. We need to save it.
不行
Do not.
我们需要把它做成死藤水
We need to turn into caapi.
这是世界上仅存的亚库纳了
It is the last leg of yakruna the world.
你应该与他们同行
You should join him.
你怎么知道?
How do you know that?
我毁了其他亚库纳
I destroyed everyone else.
这是我们仅存的希望
It is our last hope.
这是我送你的礼物
It is my gift to you.
我不是专程来听这些的
I did not come here for that.
当你来的时候，就是了
He came, yes.
我说不要
I'm saying no.
外面正在打仗
Is a war out there.
我的人民需要纯的橡胶才能获胜
My people need pure rubber to win it.
我需要带走它
I need to take it with me.
你又再说谎了吗?
You lied to me again?
又想要制造武器、带来死亡吗?
Want to make weapons and turn it into death?
快给我
Give me.
我不在乎了，杀了我吧!
Kill me! I do not care.
受死是我的职责
It is my duty to die,
但是亚库纳会和我一同消逝
but yakruna dies with me.
你也不过是魂魄，永远都是
You are also Chullachaqui, and will be forever.
脱掉上衣吧
Throw shirt.
让我看看你的背后
Let me see your back.
这是美多拉死藤，是最强悍的
This is medora caapi, the most powerful of all.
它在万物诞生前已经存在
It existed before creation,
在蟒蛇降下以前
before the snake down.
它会带你去见祂
It will take you to see her.
祂非常巨大、恐怖，但你无须害怕
It is huge, frightening, but should not be afraid.
你只需要让祂拥抱
You have to let her hug.
祂的拥抱会带你到古老的深处
Her hug will take you to ancient sites,
在哪里生命并不存在，连你的胚胎也是
where life does not exist, not even your embryo.
孩子
Baby.
我曾试着杀死你
I tried to kill you.
我不配得到这个
I do not deserve this.
我也杀死了你
I also kill you.
在昨天、40年前、100年前
Before, in no time time yesterday, 40 years ago, maybe 100.
或是百万年之前
Or is there a million years.
但你依然回来了
But you came back.
我不适合教导我的族人
It was not for me to teach my people.
我应该教导你
I was supposed to teach you.
给予比他们要求更多的东西，带一首歌给他们
Give them more than they asked for. Take a song to them.
告诉他们你看见、感觉的所有事物
Tell them everything you see, everything you feel.
像一个完整的男人归来
Come back as a man of integrity.
你就是科瓦诺
You cohiuano.
库拉美卡德!
Karamakat to!
此电影受以下两部游记启发
MOVIE INSPIRED IN DIARIES OF TRAVEL:
只有少数的亚马逊文化被报导过
ONLY KNOWN REPORTS OF VARIOUS CULTURES AMAZONIAN.
献给那些从未被歌唱过的人民
DEDICATED TO PEOPLE WHOSE SONG MEMORY NEVER KNOW.
本字幕由Peace_Wang基于英文字幕翻译
- Art Subs - 7 years making art for you!
仅供学习与帮助理解剧情之用
Pirandello legend
欢迎来信指教Email:v12123310@gmail.com
Synchrony and Review lletaif | Durenkian